<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<chapter id="upgrade">
  <chapterinfo>
    <date>05.01.2004</date>

    <author>
      <firstname>Jörg</firstname>

      <surname>Lenneis</surname>

      <contrib>initial version</contrib>
    </author>

    <pubdate>05 January, 2004</pubdate>
  </chapterinfo>

  <title>Upgrading from a previous version of Netatalk</title>

  <sect1>
    <title>Overview</title>

    <para>Version 2.0 of the Netatalk suite includes significant changes and
    enhancements in functionality compared to previous versions. AFP v3.0 is
    now supported which allows UTF8 encoded filenames of up to 255 characters
    in length amongst other things. The Catalogue Node ID (CNID) subsystem has
    been reworked as well and should now be much more robust. For an overview
    of what CNIDs are and why you need them please see (Link to the section in
    configuration.xml, Bjoern?).</para>

    <para>The downside of these enhancemants is that upgrading to Netatalk 2.0
    is not a process that can be easily automated. Too many factors depend on
    site specific configuration and administrators have to make choices that
    suit their requirements. This document attempts to clarify the issues and
    outline the steps that need to be taken for a successful upgrade. As
    usual, the first of these steps should be to make a complete backup of all
    volumes and home directories that were in use with Netatalk before.
    Afterwards, you&#39;ll have to decide</para>

    <orderedlist>
      <listitem>
        <para>what encoding to use for filenames in the future and how to
        convert existing filenames</para>
      </listitem>

      <listitem>
        <para>what storage scheme to use for CNIDs and maybe convert an
        existing database to that scheme</para>
      </listitem>
    </orderedlist>

    <para>The following two sections deal with each of these areas in turn</para>
  </sect1>

  <sect1>
    <title>Filenames ...</title>

    <para>still missing ...</para>
  </sect1>

  <sect1>
    <title>Chosing a CNID storage scheme</title>

    <para>Previous versions of Netatalk allocated CNIDs either on the fly
    using a scheme called <emphasis remap="B">last</emphasis> or <emphasis
    remap="B">hash</emphasis> or CNIDs were recorded in a persistent database.
    <emphasis remap="B">hash</emphasis> generates a CNID for a file or
    directory by mangling the inode number. <emphasis remap="B">last</emphasis>
    just assigns a counter to each file and directory that is increased by one
    upon access from a client. Those numbers are only the same for a given
    file for the lifetime of the afpd process serving the client. Both schemes
    therefore violate a fundamenatal assumption: A CNID once assigned must
    never be reused for the lifetime of a volume. <emphasis remap="B">hash</emphasis>
    has disappeared from recent Netatalk releases. <emphasis remap="B">last</emphasis>
    is still supported in Netatalk 2.0 but you should think twice about using
    it in production. It will probably be OK on read only volumes, but even
    there we are not certain if OS X clients will work properly.</para>

    <para>That leaves the CNID schemes that use persistent storage for CNIDs.
    Netatalk 2.0 supports two: <emphasis remap="B">cdb</emphasis> and
    <emphasis remap="B">dbd</emphasis>. Both are based on the Berkeley DB
    database library as before. One difference is, though, that you are not
    restricted to using a single scheme for all of your volumes that has to be
    determined at compile time. The CNID scheme (also called a &#34;CNID
    backend&#34;) is now a runtime option for a volume. That means that you
    can make the choice per volume based on your reqirements. Here are the
    properties as well as the advantages and disadvantages of the three
    supported schemes: <orderedlist><listitem><para><emphasis role="bold">last:</emphasis>
    See above. Avoid, if at all possible.</para></listitem><listitem><para><emphasis
    role="bold">cdb: </emphasis>Roughly analogous to the Netatalk 1.6.x
    versions with what was called then the &#34;DID schmeme&#34; set to
    &#34;cnid&#34; and the &#34;CNID with Concurrent Data Store&#34; set to
    &#34;yes&#34;. Access to the CNID database for a volume happens directly
    from the Netatalk afpd daemons. A Berkeley DB locking scheme (the
    &#34;Concurrent Data Store&#34; bit) is used to avoid database
    inconsistencies. Robustness is much improved compared to previous
    releases. The CNID database can only become corrupted if an afpd daemon
    crashes unexpectedly, is killed by the administrator or the whole machine
    chrashes.</para></listitem><listitem><para><emphasis role="bold">bdb:</emphasis>
    There is only a single daemon that accesses the CNID database for a given
    volume. Any afpd process that wishes to retrieve or update CNIDs for that
    volume needs to do it via the daemon. The CNID database is (normally, this
    is a compile time option) updated under Berkeley DB transactional
    protection. This design combined with the transactional updates makes the
    CNID database crashproof: Any of the participating afpd daemons, the
    database daemon itself or the whole machine can crash and the CNID
    database should still be in a consistent state. The downside to this is
    that the speed of updates and retrieval is slower than with the <emphasis
    remap="B">cdb</emphasis> scheme.</para></listitem></orderedlist></para>

    <para>If you compile Netatalk 2.0 yourself and invoke configure --help,
    you&#39;ll notice that there are in fact more CNID backends to chose from.
    Don&#39;t use any of them. They are either broken or incomplete. Some of
    them might turn into something useful in the future.</para>

    <sect2>
      <title>How to upgrade if no persistent CNID storage was used</title>

      <para>That is easy. Just pick a CNID backend from above, configure it
      properly in afpd.conf and the AppleVolumes file and start up the
      necessary Netatalk processes. The databases will be automatically
      created in a subdirectory .AppleDB of the volume in question.</para>
    </sect2>

    <sect2>
      <title>How to upgrade if a persistent CNID storage scheme was used</title>

      <para>In that case the CNID databases need to be upgraded. A script
      called cnid2_create that comes with Netatalk 2.0 does most of the work.
      The steps you have to take depend on what version of Berkeley DB is
      installed on your system. If you already use one of the supported
      versions of Berkeley DB (4.0.14, 4.1.25 or 4.2.50) for your old Netatalk
      installation and plan to use it for Netatalk 2.0 as well just use the
      db_dump and db_load utilities that came with it as indicated below.
      Otherwise it is probably best to have the old and the new (to be used
      with Netatalk 2.0) version of Berkeley DB installed side by side until
      you have finished the upgrade. The reason for this is that we will dump
      out the old databases with the currently installed version of Berkeley
      DB in ASCII format and reload them with the new version. This avoids any
      incompatibility problems between Berkeley DB releases with respect to
      the on-disk format.</para>

      <para>For each volume to be upgraded, follow these steps
      <itemizedlist><listitem><para>Stop all afpd daemons accessing the
      volume.</para></listitem><listitem><para>Change to the database
      directory for that volume, most likely the .AppleDB subdirectory of the
      volume toplevel directory in question.</para></listitem><listitem><para>Dump
      the contents of cnid.db and didname.db using the old (installed) version
      of Berkeley DB like this:</para><programlisting> db_dump -f cnid.dump cnid.db db_dump -f didname.dump didname.db     </programlisting><para>Make
      sure the db_dump utility you are using is the correct (currently used)
      one. Use the full path to the db_dump executeable if in doubt. So if
      this database was created with Berkeley DB 3.xx installed in
      /usr/local/db3 use /usr/local/db3/bin/db_dump instead. This will create
      two files, cnid.dump and didname.dump in the current directory.</para></listitem><listitem><para>Run
      the cnid2_create script:</para><programlisting> /path/to/netatalk/bin/cnid2_create </programlisting><para>The
      script assumes that .AppleDB is a subdirctory of the volume directory to
      be upgraded. If that is not the case give the full path name of the
      volume as the first argument to cnid2_create. The script will create a
      file cnid2.dump in ASCII format.</para></listitem><listitem><para>Remove
      the old Berkeley DB environment and logfiles (if present):</para><programlisting> rm __db.* log.*</programlisting></listitem><listitem><para>Load
      cnid2.dump into the new database. You should use the db_load utility of
      Berkeley DB that will be used with version 2.0 of Netatalk. So if
      Berkeley DB 4.xx lives in /usr/local/db4 use</para><programlisting> /usr/local/db4/bin/db_load -f cnid2.dump
  cnid2.db </programlisting><para>This will create the new database file,
      cnid2.db. Remove the old database files cnid.db, didname.db and
      devino.db. The intermediate files cnid.dump, didname.dump and cnid2.dump
      can be removed now or at some later time.</para></listitem></itemizedlist></para>

      <para>If you do not want to have two versions of Berkeley DB installed
      side by side during the upgrade, you should first dump out the old
      databases as indicated above for all volumes, upgrade Berkeley DB and
      then load them with db_load. The cnid2_create script can be run before
      or after the upgrade. Berkeley DB environment and logfiles should still
      be removed before running db_load.</para>
    </sect2>

    <sect2>
      <title>How to upgrade if a persistent CNID storage scheme was used, the
      brute force approach</title>

      <para>If you are absolutely sure what you are doing, you can also just
      clear out all database files from the .AppleDB directories. They will be
      recreated, but will not contain the same CNIDs as before!! That might
      lead to all sorts of problems, like aliases not working any more on
      clients. As I said, make sure you know the consequences and don&#39;t
      mind them.</para>
    </sect2>
  </sect1>
</chapter>